<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Meditations - Eucalypto</title>
        <link>https://meditations.eucalypto.net/</link>
        <description>Recent content on Meditations - Eucalypto</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 17:41:27 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://meditations.eucalypto.net/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>What Kind of Sun are You?</title>
        <link>https://meditations.eucalypto.net/p/what-kind-of-sun-are-you/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 17:41:27 +0100</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://meditations.eucalypto.net/p/what-kind-of-sun-are-you/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://meditations.eucalypto.net/p/what-kind-of-sun-are-you/pexels-felix-mittermeier-956981.jpg" alt="Featured image of post What Kind of Sun are You?" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I love astronomy and the universe. I also love analogies between distant topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this analogy I have to tell you one thing about stars which are just suns. They differ by &lt;em&gt;size/mass&lt;/em&gt; and it determines most properties of a sun. In particular: the larger the size/mass, the brighter the sun shines, the hotter it is, and the &lt;strong&gt;shorter&lt;/strong&gt; it lives!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, I observe the same with motivation and people. The hotter they burn for something, the stronger their motivation. But this motivation is then often fragile: when it runs cold, trouble awaits. Before that happens, people say phrases like &amp;ldquo;keep the momentum rolling&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;let&amp;rsquo;s use that energy&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue giant is an example of a large but short lived star, whereas a Red Dwarf would be a small but long-lived one. When a blue giant reaches the end of its lifetime, it explodes in a supernova, but I think this is where the analogy starts to break down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe a better analogy would be surfing (wave riding). Or: surfing the shockwave of a supernova! But that&amp;rsquo;s enough analogies for one day. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question in the title is misleading and implies false assumptions. It implies that one person behaves consistently in a certain way. But I observed myself behaving in both ways!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hot, passionate motivation is hard to manage for me. I&amp;rsquo;m full of energy but have to pay close attention to direct it in a productive direction. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to get lost in details and let the energy go to waste. And after it is gone, I&amp;rsquo;m regularly confused as to where to go next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slow-burning kind of motivation is a lot easier to handle. I feel in control all the time and have mental capacity to look for the direction for the next milestone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But there are many questions left&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is one of those kinds superior to the other?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can I reliably create the hot one? It seems to come randomly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the right mix of those two to have a good life?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>How to read Books</title>
        <link>https://meditations.eucalypto.net/p/how-to-read-books/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 23:28:45 +0100</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://meditations.eucalypto.net/p/how-to-read-books/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://meditations.eucalypto.net/p/how-to-read-books/pexels-polina-zimmerman-3747507.jpg" alt="Featured image of post How to read Books" /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;goodread-challenge&#34;&gt;Goodread Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Goodreads, you may have received a notification for the &lt;em&gt;2021 Goodreads Reading Challenge&lt;/em&gt;. There you can set your goal for how many books you want to read this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But is the number of read books a good measure?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m reminded of &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodhart%27s_law&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Goodhart&amp;rsquo;s Law&lt;/a&gt; here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-become-better-at-book-reading&#34;&gt;How to become better at book-reading?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read books for pleasure, you may ignore everything here. But then you would also not care about how much books you read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, book reading is important and consequently, I want to achieve a certain level of professionalism. This includes both book selection and actual reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I know which book will bring me the most benefits?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I measure the benefits &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; I have read a book?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a step back. What we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; say is this: if you have read a book and &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt; did change, the book was ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-can-change&#34;&gt;What can change?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see two areas where change is possible:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mindset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action is what you and others see you do. The Mindset is trickier to see but it still shows in subtle ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if neither your actions, nor your mindset have changed, then we may argue that the book is useless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-make-sure-something-does-change&#34;&gt;How to make sure something does change?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this is a good question! We have to make more experiments and meditations about this!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
